All right. So, back to vector addition and multiplication by numbers.
好了 回到向量加法和向量与数字的乘法上来
After all, every topic in linear algebra is going to center around these two operations.
毕竟线性代数的每个话题都离不开这两种运算
Luckily, each one's pretty straightforward to define.
好在这两种运算的定义都很简单
Let's say we have two vectors,
假设我们有两个向量
one pointing up and a little to
一个从原点出发朝向右上方
the right and the other one pointing right and down a bit.
另一个从原点出发朝向右下方
To add these two vectors,
要让这两个向量相加
move the second one so that its tail sits at the tip of the first one.
就要移动第二个向量 使其尾部落在第一个向量的头部上
Then, if you draw a new vector from the tail
此时 如果你从第一个向量的尾部出发
of the first one to where the tip of the second one now sits,
到第二个向量的头部为止 绘制一个新向量
that new vector is their sum.
这个新向量就是两个旧向量的和
This definition of addition by the way,
向量加法的这个定义
is pretty much the only time in
在线性代数中 基本是
linear algebra where we let vectors stray away from the origin.
向量唯一不在原点的时候
Now, why is this a reasonable thing to do?
为什么可以这么做呢？
Why this definition of addition and not some other one?
为什么加法的定义是这样的？ 为什么不能是其它情况呢？
Well, the way I like to think about it is that each vector represents a certain movement,
我自己的理解是 每个向量都代表了一种特别的运动
a step with a certain distance and direction in space.
或者说是一步 这一步在空间里有一定的距离和方向
If you take a step along the first vector,
如果你沿着第一个向量走一步
then take a step in the direction and distance described by the second vector,
然后沿着第二个向量描述的方向和距离再走一步
the overall effect is just the same as if you
总体效果
move along the sum of those two vectors to start with.
就和你沿着两个向量的和走动是一样的
You can think about this as an extension of how we
这个过程
think about adding numbers on a number line.
有点像是用数轴的思路做加法
One way that we teach kids to think about this,
教孩子的时候
say with 2 + 5 is to think of moving
我们说 2 + 5 就相当于
two steps to the right followed by another five steps to the right.
朝右走两步 然后再朝右走五步
The overall effect is the same as if you just took seven steps to the right.
总体效果就和你直接朝右走七步是一样的
In fact, let's see how vector addition looks numerically.
我们来看看怎么用数字表示向量加法
The first vector here has coordinates 1,2.
第一个向量的坐标是 [1 , 2]
And the second one has coordinates 3,-1.
第二个向量的坐标是 [3 , -1]
When you take the vector sum using this tip to tail method,
用这个头对尾的方法为向量求和时
you can think of a four-step path from the origin to the tip of the second vector.
你可以想象一条从原点走到第二个向量头部的四步路径
Walk one to the right then two up then three to the right then one down.
先朝右走一步 然后朝上走两步 朝右走三步 然后朝下走一步
Reorganizing these steps so that you first do all of the rightward motion,
换种走法 你可以先朝右走到尽头
then do all the vertical motion,
再上下走动
you can read it saying first move 1 + 3 to the right,
你可以说第一步是朝右走 1 + 3 步
then move 2 - 1 up.
然后朝上走 2 - 1 步
So, the new vector has coordinates 1 + 3 and 2 + -1.
所以新向量的坐标是 [1 + 3 , 2 + (-1) ]
In general, vector addition in this list of
推导出来 用这种数字列表进行向量相加
numbers conception looks like matching up their terms and adding each one together.
其实就是将向量相应的项分别相加
The other fundamental vector operation is multiplication by a number.
另一种向量基本运算是向量与数字相乘
Now this is best understood just by looking at a few examples.
这用几个例子说明最好了
If you take the number two and multiply it by a given vector,
让某个向量和 2 相乘
it means you stretch out that vector so that it's two times as long as when you started.
就相当于你把这个向量拉长了一倍
If you multiply that vector by say one third,
如果让向量乘以 1/3
it means you squish it down and so that it's one third the original length.
就相当于你把向量的长度压缩成原本的 1/3
When you multiply it by a negative number like negative 1.8,
如果向量乘以负值 比如乘以 -1.8
then the vector first gets flipped around then stretched out by that factor of 1.8.
那向量会先翻转 然后拉长为原来的 1.8 倍
This process of stretching or squishing or sometimes
这个向量拉伸、压缩或翻转的过程
reversing the direction of a vector is called scaling.
叫作缩放
And whenever you catch a number like two or one third or
那些用来缩放向量的数字
negative 1.8 acting like this scaling some vector,
比如 2、1/3、-1.8
you call it a scalar.
叫做标量
In fact, throughout Linear Algebra,
事实上 纵观线性代数
one of the main things that numbers do is scale vectors.
数字的主要作用之一就是缩放向量
So, it's common to use the word scalar pretty much interchangeably with the word number.
所以标量和数字这两个词经常可以相互替换
Numerically, stretching out a vector by a factor of say,
从数字的角度来看 比如用系数 2 缩放向量
two corresponds with multiplying each of its components by that factor two.
就相当于让向量各元素分别乘以系数 2
So, in the conception of vectors as lists of numbers,
所以如果把向量当数字列表来看
multiplying a given vector by a scalar means
向量乘以标量
multiplying each one of those components by that scalar.
就相当于让标量分别乘以向量的各元素
You'll see in the following videos what I mean when I say that
观看接下来的视频 你就知道为什么我要说
linear algebra topics tend to revolve around these two fundamental operations,
线性代数基本上是围着这两种基本运算
vector addition and scalar multiplication.
向量加法和标量乘法转的了
So, they're your vector basics and in the next video,
向量的基础知识就介绍到这里了 下个视频
I'll start getting into some pretty neat concepts surrounding vectors like span,
我要介绍一些很酷的向量概念
basis and linear dependence. See you then.
比如张成空间、基和线性相关 下个视频见